Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Art Association Records 1909-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Art Association Records 1909-1969
Ann Arbor Art Association.
Constitution, by-laws, minutes of meetings, reports, membership lists, scrapbooks, correspondence and exhibit materials.
85621 Bp 2; BP outsize
2.5 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records came from different sources. Professor Emil Lorch (donor no. 2647 ) deposited three of the Association's early minute books in 1956. In 1958, the Association itself (donor no. 3459 ) began to deposit records. In 1958, Mrs. Robert Horton donated a scrapbook to the record group.
The collection is open for research.
The Ann Arbor Art Association was formed in 1909 by a group of local artists and University of Michigan art department faculty members who wished to further their talents and interests by collaborating with like-minded people in the community. Their first exhibit home was in Alumni Memorial Hall. The Association continued to hold exhibits, both juried and non-juried, in the Hall until the 1940s when it moved to the galleries of the Rackham building.
As the Association gained members, it began to expand its focus to include the promotion of art appreciation in and around Ann Arbor. Examples included the Youth Art Shows, which showcased the work of local school children, and the very successful Christmas Exhibits and Sales. The Association also exhibited members' artwork at City Hall and the Ann Arbor District Library, a practice that has continued to this day. In 1960, the Association collaborated with the Ann Arbor Merchants Association on the Ann Arbor Street Craft Fair, an exhibition and sale that quickly gained fame and popularity.
Although these records end in 1969, the Ann Arbor Art Association continues to be an active and vital group, promoting a love of art and enabling amateur artists in the community to foster their talent and love for various medium of artistic expression.
The records of the Ann Arbor Art Association cover a sixty year span and consist of meeting minutes, treasurer's reports, membership lists and materials, exhibit notices, lists of participating artists and their work, newspaper clippings covering the various exhibits, and other records of community involvement. The bulk of the records is concentrated on the administration of the Association and its exhibits and outreach programs. Many of these records were collected and maintained by Mrs. Roy Holmes, a life member of the Association, and Professor Jean Paul Slusser, the official historian of the Association during the 1950s and 1960s. The record group has been divided into two series: Organizational Records and Exhibits and Outreach.
Subjects:
Art--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Arts--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.
- Organizational Records
  The Organizational Records series is comprised of two subseries: Secretary's and other officers record books and Miscellaneous Administrative Records.
  - Secretary's and other officers record books
    The Secretary's and other officers record books subseries documents the meetings and administration of the Association. This subseries includes board and annual meeting minutes, treasurer's reports, and committee reports. There is some overlap in the dates as some of the volumes were probably maintained by different Association officers.
    - Minutes May 1909-July 1968
      - May 1909-January 1916 (Box 1)
        (lacking 1913)
      - January 1916-December 1923 (Box 1)
      - January 1924-November 1933 (Box 1)
      - January 1934-June 1946 (Box 1)
      - October 1946-May 1953 (Box 1)
      - May 1949-June 1953 (Box 1)
      - 1947-May 1950 (Box 1)
      - May 1952-May 1957 (Box 1)
      - June 1956-May 1957 (Box 1)
      - July 1953-August 1959 (Box 1)
        (also treasurer's reports)
      - November 1956-May 1962 (Box 1)
      - May 1962-July 1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative Records
    The Miscellaneous Administrative Records subseries consists of a variety of Association files including treasurer's reports, the constitution and membership records. The membership files include the lists of Association members, honorary members, and honorary life members from the earliest part of the Association's history to the final dates covered by this record group. It also includes a Members Record Book containing the artistic profiles of many 1955 Association members.
    - Correspondence 1911-1912, 1959-1963, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports May 1951-May 1966 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports May 1954-January 1961 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and Amendments 1959-1963 (Box 1)
    - Policy on Expenditure 1946, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Insurance for Art Exhibits 1958-1961, 1963-1967 (Box 1)
    - Tax Problem January 1964 (Box 1)
    - Membership
      - Membership Books and Letters 1922, 1958-1967 (Box 2)
      - Lists 1953-1969
        - 1953-1964 (Box 2)
        - 1964-1969 (Box 2)
      - Members Record January 1955 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      (include constitutions, scattered minutes, speech of president, etc.)
- Exhibits and Outreach
  The Exhibits and Outreach series documents the many and varied exhibits planned and executed by the Association from its earliest days to the late sixties. It contains the exhibit notices that were mailed to the membership, along with an extensive collection of newspaper clippings that cover the exhibits themselves. Various regular exhibit sites throughout the community, such as the Old German Restaurant, City Hall, the Ann Arbor District Library, and the annual shows - the Youth Show, the Christmas Sales and One Day Craft Shows, the Annual Members Shows, and the Ann Arbor Street Fair - are documented by planning notes, lists of participating artists and works, and press releases. The Semi-Centennial of the Association, celebrated in 1959, is also covered quite extensively. Three scrapbooks are also included in this series, spanning the thirties to the early sixties and containing exhibit notices and newspaper clippings from various exhibits.
  - Paper by Emil Lorch entitled, "The Ann Arbor Art Association Exhibits and Lectures 1909-1934; notes on the establishment of lecture course in the History of Art and on art instruction University of Michigan" August 1956 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit Notices and Newspaper Clippings
    - 1925-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1929-1931 (Box 2)
    - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
    - 1934-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 2)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1942 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1948 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1967 (Box 2)
  - Titled exhibits
    - Ann Arbor Art Association Permanent Collection 1958-1966 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Street Fair 1960, 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Christmas Shows 1958-1961, 1963 (Box 2)
    - City Hall Shows 1958-1959, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - City Hall Show 1963 (Box 2)
    - City Hall Shows December 1963, February 1964 (Box 2)
    - City Planning Shows 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Group Shows 1959, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Film Lecture Program 1951-1964 (Box 2)
    - Library Shows 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Water Color Exhibit 1959 (Box 2)
    - Old German Restaurant 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - One Day Craft Sale 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Semi-Centennial 1959 (Box 2)
    - Jean Paul Slusser Tribute Fund 1964 (Box 2)
    - Youth Exhibit 1960-1966 (Box 2)
    - Exhibit Notices 1957-1967 (Box 2)
    - Various 1954-1964 (Box 3)
      (includes press releases, price lists)
    - Various 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - Publication: Hand-book for the first exhibition of the Ann Arbor Art Association, 1909 (Box 3)
    - Publication: Exhibition of oriental and American Art, 1910 (Box 3)
    - Publication: Retrospective exhibition ...Warren P. Lombard ...Horatio W. Shaw, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Publication: The Ann Arbor Art Association 1909-1959 a survey of fifty years, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook containing exhibit notices and newspaper clippings 1931-1938 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook containing exhibit notices and newspaper clippings 1948-1954 (Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook containing exhibit notices and newspaper clippings 1953-1962 (Volume 2)
    - Attendance book for Art Association exhibits in Alumni Memorial Hall 1935-1936 (Box 3)